这是阿波罗11号——人类历史上第一次登月的画面
This is Apollo 11, landing on the Moon for the first time in human history.
着陆后几秒钟，尼尔·阿姆斯特朗说
Just a few seconds after touchdown, Neil Armstrong said
“这里是静海基地。‘鹰’着陆成功。”
“Tranquility Base here, the Eagle has landed”.
静海基地是NASA选择作为人类首次登月的着陆地点
Tranquility Base was the name that NASA had chosen for the site of the first Moon landing.
它位于月球平原“静海”的西南角
It’s located in the south-western corner of the Lunar plain called Mare Tranquillitatis
意为“宁静之海”
or “Sea of Tranquility”.
它只是月球上千个以其地理学特点命名的名字之一
This is just one out of thousands of names that have been given to geographical features on the Moon.
那这名字是谁钦定的？
But who is in charge of coming up with these names?
是官方名字吗？
And are they official?
本期视频我们就来学习一个如何给月球地点命名
In this video we’re going to look at how we began naming features on the Moon.
我们还将了解谁负责让名字成为官方名称
We’re also going to look at who’s in charge of making these names official
以及为月球地名命名的严格规则
and the strict rules around naming a place on the Moon.
1610年，伽利略公布了他著名的月球画像
In the year 1610, Galileo released his famous drawings of the Moon.
利用世界上第一架望远镜，他能更“近距离”研究月球
Looking through one of the world’s very first telescopes, he studied the moon closely
并能够对月球画像以准确表现月球崎岖不平的表面
and was able to produce drawings which accurately represented the Moon’s harsh features
而这种方法其他人从未做过
in a way that no one else had ever seen before.
虽然伽利略绘制出第一份月球地图
Although Galileo had essentially created the very first map of the Moon,
但地图上却没标地名
there were no place names on this map.
40年后，天文学家里乔利和格里马尔迪绘制了一份新的月球地图
40 years later, a new map of the Moon was created by astronomers Riccioli and Grimaldi.
这份地图将月球分成8块区域
This map divided the Moon up into 8 sections
而每块区域中的高山、平原则被命名为“宁静”、“澄净”等
and names like ‘Tranquility’ and ‘Serenity’ were given to the great mountains and flat plains that lay in between.
该地图很快变成月球地名命名基础，其中好多名字沿用至今
This map quickly became the basis for naming the Moon’s features and many of the original names are still used to this day.
几个世纪后，人类航天事业正式起步
Fast forward by a few centuries and we have the birth of spaceflight.
1959年，苏联第一次把探测器送到月球背面
In 1959, the Soviets became the first to send a probe to the far side of the moon.
它让人类首次看到月球背面的画面
This probe successfully imaged the side of the Moon which had never been seen before by humans.
有了月球背面的画面
With this new perspective of the Moon’s hidden surface,
苏联开始用他们的英雄和地名为月球上的地方命名
the Soviets started to name features after Russian Heroes and place names.
齐奥尔科夫斯基环形山
Циолковский
莫斯科海
Море Москвы
之后十年，美苏两国开始收集大量更清晰的月球背面照片
Over the next decade, America and The Soviets started to piece together higher quality images of the far side of the Moon
并为新地名命名
whilst continuing to name newly found features.
虽然NASA经常给月球添加非正式地名
Although NASA often informally names features on the Moon,
但他们根本没有权力去正式给月球上的地名命名
they don’t actually have any authority to officially assign names to lunar features.
当为其他星球的地名命名时
When naming features on other planetary bodies,
每个名字都必须被国际天文联合会接受
each name has to be accepted by the International Astronomical Union.
但不止有NASA，任何人都可以向IAU提交命名
However, it’s not just NASA that can suggest names, anyone can submit a name to the IAU
只要其符合他们的一些特定的原则
as long as it complies with their specific guidelines.
月球上的环形山(陨石坑)必须以已故科学家、探险家的名字命名
Almost all craters on the Moon must be named after deceased scientists or explorers who
且他们必须在自己的领域有过杰出贡献
have made a significant contribution to their field.
月球上大平原之类的地名必须起拉丁文名字
The large plains that are so common on the Moon must be given Latin names
意义必须是类似天气等的抽象概念
which describe things like weather and other abstract concepts.
月球上发现的山脊之类，必须以地球科学家的名字命名
Ridges like these which are found on the Moon have to be named specifically after Geoscientists.
虽然这些名字可能和科学界很多著名人士有关
Although these names may be attached to significant people within the science community,
但其大小一般反映不出命名者的科学贡献大小
the scale of a Lunar feature doesn’t necessarily reflect who it’s named after.
哥白尼和阿基米德环形山在月球上都非常大
Copernicus and Archimedes both have their names attached to spectacularly large craters,
但其他科学界传奇人物比如伽利略、牛顿这些名字的环形山则很小
whereas other science legends like Galileo and Newton were given features that are much less impressive.
在1970年，IAU同意将月球最大的环形山之一命名为“阿波罗环形山”
In 1970, the IAU agreed to name one of the widest craters on the Moon ‘Apollo’
而阿波罗环形山中的小环形山则用阿波罗8、11号宇航员的名字命名
and smaller craters within Apollo were named after astronauts from the Apollo 8 and Apollo 11 missions.
附近的环形山也在之后用NASA已故员工命名
Nearby craters were later named after deceased NASA employees,
其中包括阿波罗1号、两架航天飞机灾难中丧生的宇航员
including the lost crew of Apollo 1 and the two Space Shuttle disasters.
虽然现在这些名字我们大多不认识
So although these names might not be familiar to us now,
当未来太空旅行成为现实的时候
in the future when space tourism is a reality,
阿波罗、博尔曼、洛弗尔这些地名或许会和纽约、巴黎、东京一样家喻户晓
places like Apollo, Borman and Lovell might be as common to us as New York, Paris and Tokyo.
字幕翻译给虫，欢迎点赞投币收藏分享转发评论关注充电~
感谢PrimalSpace频道的支持者为每次视频制作提供的帮助
Thank you to the Primal Space patrons who help to write and research each video.
如果您想为PrimalSpace频道做出贡献并加入我们的专有Discord群
If you'd like to contribute to Primal Space and join our exclusive Discord,
欢迎前往Patreon.com/PrimalSpace
please visit Patreon.com/PrimalSpace,
满100名赞助者将抽三人送坎巴拉太空计划
where we will be giving away 3 copies of Kerbal Space Program once we reach 100 Patrons.
最后记得关注，方便我们随时讨论共同学习太空有关的知识
So make sure you're subscribed so you can in join the discussion as we continue to learn more about all things space.
感谢观看，我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.